Xing!
六娘啊
Where do I start with you?
你让我怎么说你
What you just expressed,
你刚才的一番陈情
your loyalty to the Ministry of Justice,
对我刑部的忠心
is as clear as day.
那是天日可鉴
It's truly moving.
令人动容
But saying such things to Lord Lai
但是你当着来中丞
is really not a good idea!
这么说属实太大胆了呀
[He is, after all,]
那可是
the Dark Demon!
黑罗刹
My Lord!
大人大人
Indeed, Xing!
是啊 六娘
My heart is still racing.
我现在吓得心还慌呢
Do you really believe you
你是真以为自个儿
are literally a she-devil?
是母夜叉呢
You know...
那
That Dark Demon is someone
那问题那黑罗刹
who can really rip out real
便是遇到了夜叉恶鬼
devils or demons' hearts
都能把心
and eat them raw!
剖开给吃了的主
What's the point
你说
[of getting under his skin?]
咱惹他干什么呢
[Princess Ying has arrived.]
英王殿下到
Greetings, Your Highness.
拜见英王殿下
With your intelligence and skills,
沈夫人聪慧
you're adept at both detective work
既能留心查案
and household management.
又能持家有方
You're indeed
当真是
a rare female talent.
难得一见的女英才
We promote the participation of
我朝鼓励女子入朝为官
women in governance.
巾帼亦可出将入相
As the wife of Mr Yan,
阁领夫人
you are a paragon of this vision.
可算得上是个中表率了
Gratitude, Your Highness.
多谢英王殿下抬爱
May I ask what brings
不知殿下此番前来
you here today?
所为何事
Last night, Chen Huo'e returned from the dead.
昨夜陈火蛾死而复生
This morning,
今晨
Lord Lai approached Her Highness
来中丞便向太皇太后
to request the authority to investigate.
讨要了查案之权
This case is entangled and complex.
此案个中纠缠复杂
I imagine the Ministry of Justice
想来刑部
would not want to get involved, right?
也不愿意纠缠吧
It's originally
此案
handled by the IG.
原先由内卫府审理
But it's been taken over by Lord Lai.
如今由来中丞重审
We have no authority to intervene,
我刑部自是无权过问
nor do we dare to do it.
亦不敢过问
However, Yan Xing,
可颜幸
besides being a clerk in the Ministry,
除了是刑部书吏
is also the wife of Lord Commander.
更是大阁领夫人啊
I heard you're so good
听闻沈夫人
at managing your husband.
御夫颇有心得
If you could
你若是
persuade him not to
能够劝导你的夫君
get involved in this case,
不要牵扯此案
and manage to suppress your curiosity
自己也能忍得住好奇
to stay out of it,
作壁上观
I would be very willing
本宫倒是很愿意
to help you
成人之美
personally go to Her Royal Highness
亲自向太皇太后
to request a decree for marriage,
讨要圣旨赐婚
so that your sister and Han Shiyuan
让你那三姐和韩世元
can be together.
可以有情人终成眷属
I am quite busy.
本宫可是很忙的
Don't make me wait for you too long.
还望沈夫人尽早答复
Is that alright?
好吗
Xing!
六娘
Yan Xing.
颜六娘
You originally had nothing
你本来跟那案子
to do with that case.
就没有关系
All you need to do is
你只要好好地
to persuade Lord Commander.
劝劝大阁领
Then your family can receive
那你们颜家
2 marriage decrees granted
就能得两份
by Her Royal Highness.
太皇太后恩赐的婚约呀
How glorious
那是多么光宗耀祖
and prestigious is that!
光耀门楣的事
What were you hesitating for?
你犹豫什么呀
Why didn't you
刚才为什么
agree immediately earlier?
不立刻答应了呢
[Princess Ying and Lord Lai]
那永安公主和来中丞
clearly don't want Imperial Guard and
明显就是不想让
the Ministry of Justice involved.
内卫府和刑部参与此案
But the more they act this way,
可是他们越这样
the more it shows their guilt, doesn't it?
就显得越心虚不是吗
Moreover, logically speaking,
而且按理来说
Princess Ying
永安公主
has just escaped from the suspicion
刚从佛陀吞罪案的
of the weeping statue case.
嫌疑中脱身
Why would she rush to
那她何必又急哄哄的
stir up the hornet's nest?
来蹚这趟浑水呢
Xing!
六娘
This case is clearly a tangled web.
这摆明了就是个血坑
You should be avoiding it.
这躲都还来不及
You wouldn't want to get involved, right?
你不会真的想往里跳吧
Chui!
垂垂
Yan Xing! You lousy little...
颜六娘
You are Lord Commander's wife.
你是大阁领夫人
I can't control what risks you take.
你要顶什么雷我管不了
But you must not
但是你休要
link this case to us
将此事和我们刑部
in any way.
扯上一丝一毫的关系
The Ministry of Justice
我们刑部
will not accompany you to your grave!
不给你陪葬
My Lord,
主事
Lord Zhang Baohuan,
太皇太后近前的
a confidant of Her Royal Highness
张宝环张侍郎
is currently outside our ministry.
此刻刑部门外落轿
He asked
说
Lady Yan to join him for a chat.
请颜书吏往前一叙
Dear heavenly nymph!
祖宗
[Please stop bringing all these]
别给我招惹
[mighty and influential figures]
这满天神佛了
to my humble ministry!
我刑部庙小装不下
Lady Yan.
颜大人
Your schedule seems full.
颜大人事务繁忙
Today Baohuan came for a chat.
今日宝环前来拜访
I hope this is not an intrusion.
您不会介意吧
I'm truly humbled.
下官不敢
I came today,
我今日前来呢
not to ask anything major,
也没有什么大事要问
but just to inquire
就是想问问
about Han Shiyuan's recent situation.
韩世元近日
Is he doing well?
可还安好
Last night, he returned to the
韩郎君昨夜
Yan residence with my sister.
便跟三姐一起回了颜府
Imperial Guard didn't give him a hard time.
内卫府并未为难他
I went to the Yan residence today,
我今日去了颜府啊
but was told he was not there.
被告知不在府内
It seems he
那看来他
still doesn't want to see me, right?
还是不想见我吧
If I may, can I inquire about
不知张侍郎跟韩郎君
your shared history?
有何渊源
He is just
没什么
an old acquaintance.
就是旧相识罢了
Since he has won the favor
既然韩世元
of the Yan Family's third daughter,
深得颜家三娘子的垂青
that is indeed his fortune.
那也是他的造化呀
In the future, I would be
日后
grateful if you could extend your care
您有机会一定要在府中
to him within your household.
多多照拂一二
Certainly.
自然
Then,
那
Baohuan will not disturb you any longer.
宝环就不打扰了
I will take my leave now.
先告辞
[Han Shiyuan is very secretive about]
韩世元对自己与张宝环
[his relationship with Zhang Baohuan]
和永安公主的关系
[and Princess Ying.]
讳莫如深
[Behind Chen Huo'e's resurrection,]
陈火蛾死而复生的背后
[there seem to be many parties involved.]
似乎也有诸多势力牵连
[It even seems to involve]
甚至牵扯到了
[Caiwei's marriage.]
三姐的婚事
[Even Lai Luozhi wants to intervene.]
连来罗织都想插手此事
[Now,]
如今
[it seems everyone hopes]
似乎所有人都希望
[that I could stay out of it.]
我不要牵涉其中
[What should I do?]
我该怎么办
Xing, you've come.
六娘你来了
Greetings, Caiwei,
三姐
Mr. Han.
韩郎君
We are indebted to you and Lord Commander
昨夜还要多谢
for your rescue last night.
你和大阁领
Why did you send gifts to us?
今日怎么还特意送礼
Lady Yan
沈夫人
must be here to interrogate us, right?
怕是来提审问话的吧
About last night,
昨夜之事
the two of us
我和韩郎
really know nothing.
真的什么都不知道
Caiwei, rest assured.
三姐你放心
The truth of last night's incident
昨夜的案情
will definitely come to light.
一定会水落石出的
I'm just here to ask
我只是想知道
Mr. Han.
韩郎君
What is your relationship with Lord Zhang
你跟张侍郎和永安公主
and Princess Ying?
是什么关系
There is nothing I can reveal.
无可奉告
Even now,
都这个时候了
you keep it concealed.
你还无可奉告
If it weren't for you,
若不是因为你
how would my sister
我姐姐她怎么会
have suffered so much?
遭这么大的罪
Don't pressure him anymore.
你就别逼韩郎了
I trust him.
我信他
Xing, welcome home.
六娘回来了
Mother.
阿娘
Aren't you on duty today?
你今日不用当值吗
You must be worried about those gifts.
你一定是担心那些礼物
So you're here
想亲自到
to check them,
你三姐那儿看看
right?
是不是
You know,
我跟你说
your husband
这次姑爷
has handled the matter with grace,
那做得可妥帖了
even bringing
你娘啊
honor to me.
脸上都跟着有光
Gifts?
礼物
Caiwei also mentioned gifts earlier.
刚才三姐也提到了送礼
What exactly are you all talking about?
你们到底在说什么呀
Don't you know?
你不知道吗
This morning, the Shens sent someone over,
今早沈府派人来慰问
saying you were worried about your sister
说是你担心你三姐
being frightened last night,
昨夜受了惊吓
and specially sent
特意送了
a whole bunch of nourishing supplements.
一大堆的补品礼物
When I saw how generous they were,
我一看那出手阔绰
I knew
就知道
it must be from my son-in-law.
肯定是姑爷掏的钱
By the way, the kitchen
对了
is stewing some nourishing soup.
厨房炖了补品
Come,
走
let me get some for you.
给你来一碗去
Shen Du?
沈渡
He actually did all this behind my back.
他居然瞒着我做了这些
Why has he suddenly become
他怎么会对我们家
so warm towards my family?
突然这么热情啊
Isn't that obvious?
那还用说
It's all thanks to you!
肯定是沾了你的光啊
Otherwise, how would Lord Commander
要不然人家堂堂大阁领
care about our insignificant Yan Family?
怎么会关心小小颜府
That bastard!
那个臭小子
He wouldn't still be harboring
该不会贼心不死
feelings for Caiwei, would he?
还惦记你三姐吧
Your sister is celebrated
那你三姐
as a gifted maiden in Xiang'an!
可是襄安才女啊
She does seem more
确实看上去比你
appealing than you.
更招人惦记啊
No, no, no!
不行不行
This trend
这个苗头
must be nipped in the bud.
必须得给他掐灭
Tonight, I will urge your father
今晚我就去撺掇你爹
to arrange the marriage
让他赶紧给
between Caiwei and Han Shiyuan.
三娘和韩世元办成婚
We need to make sure they
得赶紧让他们
get married as soon as possible.
生米煮成熟饭了才行
Mother!
阿娘
Exactly what's going on
你成天都在
in your mind?
歪想些什么啊
Did White Death
那个白无常
beat you up lately?
最近没有打你吧
Have you two been arguing recently?
近期你俩可还争吵
You have to know,
阿娘跟你说啊
you must not let your guard down.
你可不能掉以轻心
You need to keep
必须看牢
a close watch on him.
万万不可松懈
OK, mother, I understand.
好 阿娘 我知道了
I am a bit hungry.
我突然有点饿了
Why don't you go get me some soup?
要不然你去给我盛碗汤
I almost forgot about it.
我又差点给忘了
Just wait a moment.
你等着
Quite an exquisite pipa.
好琴
Lovely melody.
好曲
What a beautiful sentiment.
好意韵啊
Today, the piece played
今日金藏所弹曲目
seems different from before.
仿佛与以往不同
It has a touch of Zen.
多了几分禅意
Listening to it is refreshing.
听来叫人神清气爽
This is an ancient masterpiece
这是徐内司
sought by Lady Xu.
寻来的古曲雅乐
A few days ago, when I went to the temple,
臣前几日进寺礼佛时
I received the score from an eminent monk.
得一高僧相赠曲谱
It's said to have an enlightening effect.
据说有清明灵台之效
So I asked Mr. Jin
这便求了金乐师
to play it for you.
雅奏一番
Indeed, it is wonderful.
果然甚妙
Back in the day,
哀家记得
you personally
当年
went up the mountain to dig rare
是你亲自上山挖了灵芝
mushrooms for me,
送给我
asking me to go easy on
求我将沈家的案子
the Shens
从轻发落
and release Shen Du from custody.
放年轻的沈渡出罪容所
Then,
那今日
what is your request today?
是何要求啊
I am truly humbled.
臣不敢
He may enter now.
宣他进来吧
Mr Shen.
沈爱卿啊
I know why you're here.
哀家知你所为何来
Lord Lai has requested
来中丞
to lead the Chen Huo'e investigation.
自请重审陈火蛾一案
The case
这案子
has been handled by you recently.
虽然近日由你查办
But it's previously under
但毕竟五年前
his supervision 5 years ago.
是他办理的
He admitted that he's failed in his duties.
他自陈失职
It is only natural for him
目前想戴罪立功
to demand compensation.
也是人之常情嘛
Your Highness,
太皇太后
I believe,
微臣以为
once a person dies, they die for good.
人死不可能复生
The Chen Huo'e from back then
当年的陈火蛾
may not be the same as the one of today.
未必就是近日的陈火蛾
Lord Shen,
沈爱卿啊
since you are unwell,
你既然身体抱恙
there's no need to force yourself.
就不必勉强了
It's a mere scratch,
小伤而已
and it's already healed.
早已无碍
Alright.
好
Since Lady Xu is vouching for you,
既然徐内司替你担保
then the case
那陈火蛾一案
will be assigned to the IG.
就交于内卫府办理吧
Yes, ma'am.
是
Then,
既如此
the Imperial Academy
弘文馆学子一事
should be handled by Lord Zhang.
就叫张相去办理吧
He is a civil official.
毕竟他是文臣
It would be easier for him to communicate
和学子们交流起来
with students.
也方便些
Lord Shen.
沈爱卿啊
How about you take charge of the security
你就负责近日京畿安防
of the capital region?
如何
Your Royal Highness,
太皇太后
this is a matter of vital importance.
京畿安防兹事体大
Nothing could go wrong.
不容有失
The IG lacks manpower
内卫府人手有限
for full coverage.
恐怕难以看顾周全
How cunning you are!
你这猢狲
You often lament a lack of power.
平时只嫌权职不够
But today,
今天倒好
you are making excuses.
推三阻四
Do you believe I don't know
你当哀家
what has been going on in your mind?
不知你心里想什么
I wouldn't dare.
臣不敢
Wouldn't dare?
不敢
I see that you two are scheming.
我看你们算计哀家
You are both quite bold.
胆子大得很呢
Apologies, Your Royal Highness.
太皇太后息怒 恕罪
Alright, alright.
行了行了
As I entrust you with the security,
既然将京畿安防交给你
you will be given the authority to
自然会给你
mobilize resources from offices.
调动各处的权力
During the Academy examination,
弘文馆考学期间
any matters related to security
凡涉及到安防
will be under
各地人员
your coordination.
都由你调配便是了
Gratitude, Your Royal Highness.
谢太皇太后
Your Highness!
殿下
Mr Zhang has secured the academy's task.
张相已经拿下了弘文馆
That old bastard!
老东西
He has gotten ahead again.
又让他占了先
Now, this is getting interesting.
这才有趣
Your Highness.
殿下
Sir.
老师
You came in time.
来得正好
Take a look at my yellow peony.
看看我这御衣黄牡丹
Isn't it blooming beautifully?
开得可好
Good.
好 好啊
[Your Highness.]
贤王殿下
[Her Royal Highness]
此次太皇太后
has already entrusted
将弘文馆考学一事
the examination to me.
交给老臣负责
[The students of the Imperial Academy]
这弘文馆的学子
[are the best among scholars in the realm.]
乃天下学子之首
If the examination succeeded,
有此次考学之功
[you would be]
那贤王殿下
[be even more advantageous]
得摄政王之位
to secure the position of regent.
那就是更胜一筹啊
Sir,
老师啊
whether Princess Ying
无论将来是我
or I become the regent,
还是英王做这个摄政王
we are all here to
我们都是为了
serve Her Highness and His Majesty.
太皇太后和陛下效力的
That is not correct.
贤王殿下此言差矣
His Majesty suffers from delayed speech.
这陛下语迟
Her Highness is in her twilight years.
太皇太后年迈
The regent is of utmost importance
摄政王
to the foundation of the empire.
乃大苍国基重中之重
On this matter,
就此事上
You must not be negligent.
贤王殿下切不可怠慢啊
I appreciate your dedication.
老师此番辛苦了
Please clear up misunderstandings,
切要扭转大家的误解
and show love
要让广大的寒门学子
and respect to
感受到
students from humble backgrounds.
你我之间的爱重才是
Yes.
是是是
Of course.
那是自然
However,
只不过
Shen Du has been tasked with
这次那沈渡又得了
the responsibility for the capital's security,
京畿安防之责
which gives him more power.
平白多了些权责
He is indeed capable.
沈卿自是个得力的
No matter what situation
无论这个人
he encounters or trouble
遇到了什么样的状况
he faces,
闹出什么样的乱子
he always finds a way to handle it.
他总是有办法去应对
Sir,
老师
don't you think so?
你说呢
I agree.
贤王说得是
Now that he's
那这沈渡
taken on the security task,
得了这京畿安防
[should the situation]
那襄安的局面
[in Xiang'an be a bit]
是不是应该
[more chaotic?]
越混乱越热闹才好
Your Highness,
贤王殿下
should we "help" him a bit?
我们要不要帮他一下
I beg your pardon, sir?
老师方才说什么
You may excuse yourself now.
你去忙吧
[Sir,]
大阁领
[the task of overseeing the examination]
弘文馆的考学之责
[has ultimately been given to the PM.]
终究还是交给了张相
Her Highness has entrusted the security
太皇太后将京畿安防
of the capital region to us.
交给了内卫府
Is this meant to be a consolation?
是作为安抚吗
This is exactly the outcome I desired.
这本就是我想要的结果
You don't seem disappointed.
您看起来并无失望之色
A gust of wind is coming.
要起风了
During the examination,
弘文馆考学期间
Princess Ying, Prince Xian,
英王 贤王
the PM and Lai Luozhi
张相 来罗织
will surely take action.
必定会有所行动
Keep a close watch.
盯紧了
Understood.
是
The security around the academy
弘文馆附近的安防
must not be underestimated.
不能小视
We can mobilize palace guards
可以抽调
and inspectors for assistance.
金吾卫和异良人协助
And the security of all the imperial
还有三省六部的安防
offices is the same.
也不能忽视
Keep our men there,
我内卫府亲自盯牢
especially
尤其是
the Imperial Secretariat.
麟台
Yes, sir.
是
Who is it?
是何人啊
Lord Commander!
沈大阁领
Thank you for the gifts you sent to
谢谢你给三姐她们
my family.
送的礼物
They all loved them a lot.
她们都很喜欢
Not worth mentioning.
小事
Anything interesting happened
今日的朝堂上
during the assembly today?
可有什么趣事
Not much.
没什么
Lai Luozhi requested to take over
只是来罗织
the investigation of the Chen Huo'e case.
要陈火蛾案的查案权
Did Her Royal Highness give it to him?
那太皇太后给他了吗
She gave it to me.
给了我
Hey...
你
Are you saying that the case
你是说陈火蛾案
will still be handled by the IG?
还是由内卫府审理
Bravo!
太好了
I'll go prepare ink for you.
我去给你研墨
No matter how you tidy up a puppy house,
小狗窝再怎么收拾
it will still be a puppy house.
也还是小狗窝
Is your hand
你的手
better?
好点了吗
I was bitten by a puppy.
被小狗咬了
It won't heal that fast.
哪有那么快好的
Lord Commander.
沈大阁领
Please read the case files a little.
你看看卷宗
Rest for a bit.
休息休息
How about I cook for you?
六娘去给你做饭可好
You know how to cook?
你还会做饭
Don't underestimate me.
小看我
I am the renowned Lady Yan Xing.
我可是堂堂的颜六娘
Yeah, right.
是
"She has extraordinary talents,"
咏絮之才
"proficient in writing, painting, embroidery,"
笔歌墨舞 描鸾刺凤
"and classics, and wealthy in knowledge."
经明行修 博古通今
"Her reputation as a virtuous lady"
其贤德淑女之名
"is unmatched in Xiang'an."
冠绝襄安
[Let's go.]
走
Come on.
快
Please sit.
请坐
Sir,
大阁领
I made these myself.
这都是我亲手炒的菜
Give it a try.
你尝尝看
Try this chicken.
尝尝看这个鸡肉
How is it?
如何
Surprisingly,
居然
it's not bad.
还不错
See?
看吧看吧
I told you so.
我就说
Cooking and autopsy
做饭和验尸的道理
have similar principles.
都差不多嘛
Using preservation
用保存
and dissecting methods
和解剖尸首的方式
to handle this chicken,
来处理这个鸡肉
the taste will be
做出来的口感
just like that of a freshly killed one.
就会跟刚杀掉的一样
Yeah,
对
Now, try this soup.
你再尝尝这个汤
The inspiration for using this spice
这个香料的灵感
comes from the spices used by
是来源于
Lady Tang for preserving corpses.
唐大夫人腌尸体的香料
Smell it.
你闻闻看
Isn't the aroma delightful?
是不是香气扑鼻
Isn't it?
是不是
Very fragrant, right?
很香吧
Is there something you want?
你要什么
Just say it.
直说
That fast, really?
这么快就成功了
Well,
我是想说
can I participate in
陈火蛾的案子
the case?
我能不能参与啊
No, you cannot.
不能
Can't you see
你是看不清
how complicated this case is?
这个案子有多复杂吗
The Ministry of Justice and the Supreme Court
刑部和大理寺
are both trying to avoid it.
都唯恐避之不及
And you come begging to be part of it?
你还来这儿求
I understand.
我知道
Lai Luozhi and Princess Ying
来罗织和永安公主
both came to see me today.
今日都来找过我
In both open and hidden ways,
明里暗里
they just don't want me
就是不想让我
to get involved in this case.
招惹这个案子
But I am just a
可我不过是一个
lowly clerk.
小小的书吏
Could they really be wary of me?
他们难道还忌讳我不成
What they are wary of is just
他们忌讳的
my title of "Lord Commander's wife."
不过是沈夫人这三个字
if you are aware of all this...
既然你都知道
You have already taken on this case,
你都已经接下此案了
and I am now, without a doubt,
我如今
the genuine and rightful
又是逃也逃不掉的
Lord Commander's wife.
沈夫人
How could I possibly
又如何能干干净净
escape from all this?
明哲保身呢
If you encounter danger,
如果你遇到了危险
how could I possibly remain unscathed?
我又能独善其身吗
Forgive me.
见谅
What is there to forgive?
这有什么好见谅的
Finding the truth
查明真相
and clearing one's name
还人清白
has always been my ideal.
本来也就是我的理想
I only ask
我只求
that you give me
你能给我一个
the authority to investigate.
查案的职权
Rest assured,
你放心
I will definitely not hold you back.
我绝对不会拖你后腿的
I won't be a burden to you either.
我也不会成为你的累赘
But you must promise me
但是你要先答应我
that during the investigation,
在这个案子中
if anything happens,
遇到任何事
you will discuss it with me first
都与我商量之后
before making any decisions.
再作决定
You must not act on your own.
切不可私自妄动
Of course.
当然
You are Lord Commander,
你是大阁领
my superior,
是我的上司
so I will definitely follow your command.
我自然得听你安排了
Henceforth, my allegiance
从今往后
lies solely with my Lord Commander.
唯大阁领之命是从
Is this to your liking?
可好
Silly.
无聊
Imperial Guard on duty.
内卫府查案
Is Lord Chen Shoujie here?
陈守杰大人在吗
I am Yan Xing, from the Ministry of Justice.
我是刑部书吏颜幸
I have a few questions to ask him.
有几个问题想问问他
That night, my lady was in a good mood,
那晚夫人心情很好
cooking herself.
亲自下厨
She made mutton and smoked chicken.
做了水盆羊肉和熏鸡
She also baked flatbreads and stuffed breads.
还烤了胡饼和毕罗
[She even rewarded me with a bowl of wine.]
还赏了老奴一碗酒吃呢
[I slept until midnight,]
我睡到半夜
[when I suddenly]
我就突然听到
[heard crying.]
老爷的喊叫声
[Darling!]
夫人
In the end, Her Lady...
结果夫人
Officer,
女官大人
be careful.
小心点啊
My Lord!
老爷 老爷
- My Lord! - Fire!
老爷 失火了
Fire!
失火了
- My Lord! - Moth! (Chen Huo'e's last character)
老爷 蛾
- There's a fire! - My Lord!
着火了 老爷
Moth! Moth!
蛾 蛾
Is he talking about Chen Huo'e?
莫非他说的是陈火蛾
Keep distance from the rest of us.
不要靠近大家
From now on, you just sit...
以后你就坐
Here.
这儿
Since you are working for Imperial Guard,
既然你替内卫府办案
then you have nothing to do with
以后就跟刑部
the Ministry of Justice.
没有关系了
No matter what trouble you cause,
无论你闯天大的祸
it has nothing to do with us.
都跟刑部无关
The Ministry of Justice
这趟浑水
will stay out of this case.
我们刑部不蹚
Stay out!
不蹚
Yan Xing!
颜六娘
Pay attention to me.
我告诉你
No matter what,
请你无论如何
at any time,
任何时候
you must watch your back.
都一定要保护好自己
If you die,
你要是死了
I will definitely
我定要
sing for three days
我定要在芙蓉园
at Furong Theater, so you won't
唱三天大戏
be in peace even in the afterlife.
让你死都死得不得安宁
Don't worry,
你放心
I'll definitely not let you have your way.
我一定不会让你得逞的
[In the third year of Shengli era,]
圣历三年
[Jinxiu Workshop was punished]
锦绣坊因献给
[for presenting summer clothes to]
汝宁长公主的夏衣逾制
[Princess, which exceeded the regulations.]
犯忤逆之罪
[Because they were ordered by her husband,]
因夏衣为驸马所订制
[he committed suicide on site.]
汝宁驸马当庭自杀谢罪
[From then on, Princess Runing]
汝宁长公主自此
[fell out with the Empress Dowager.]
与当今太皇太后反目
[And Jinxiu Workshop]
而锦绣坊
[was closed for using patterns]
因使用逾制图纹
[that exceeded the regulations,]
犯了皇家大忌被查封
[The owner and his family were executed.]
锦绣坊老板一家被诛
[This is the Jinxiu Workshop case.]
是为锦绣坊案
- Go. - Let go of me!
走 放开我
[Exceeding regulations.]
逾制
[It is rumored that four years ago,]
坊间流传四年前
[the princess' husband longed to be praised,]
是驸马想要表功献宝
[but unexpectedly, Princess Runing]
却不料让汝宁长公主
[wore the same purple chrysanthemum]
误穿了同先皇后一样的
[patterned clothing as the queen,]
紫菊图样服饰
[which angered]
这才惹恼了
[the current Empress Dowager.]
当今太皇太后
[And in this case file, it only]
而这卷宗中
[vaguely states "exceeding regulations."]
只敢含糊写成逾制
[Seems the case file can't be trusted.]
可见卷宗也不能尽信
[Come and take a look, flatbreads.]
来看看吧 炊饼
[Come on.]
来
Mr. Pan!
潘兄 潘兄
I didn't expect you to be working here.
没想到你居然屈才在此
It makes it difficult for us to find you.
叫我们好找啊
Who are you two?
二位是
I witnessed your quick wit
前日在弘文馆
the other day at the Imperial Academy.
就一睹潘兄才思敏捷
I heard that you are also
听闻
going to participate in the examination.
你也要参加弘文馆考学
In the future,
未来
we will be classmates!
我们便是同窗之谊啊
I am flattered.
潘驰惭愧
- Come on. - Seriously.
走走走 惭愧
We must share a drink!
必须喝一杯
- Let's go! - Come on!
走吧 走走走
Alright.
行
- This way, please!
走走走 请 这边
Mr. Pan, this way.
潘兄请
Good, good!
好 好 好
Prince Xian and Prime Minister
这是贤王殿下和张相
cherish talent.
爱才惜才
They specifically instructed us
特意嘱咐我们
to interact with the students
和此次考学的寒门学子
from humble backgrounds.
相互交流
So we can better
未来才能更好地
serve the empire in the future.
报效朝廷嘛
Mister,
这位才子
please take a seat.
快坐
No formalities.
快快请坐 不必拘礼
[His Majesty is benevolent.]
圣上仁德
[This time, the Imperial Academy]
此次弘文馆考学
[does not consider social status,]
不论门第
[family background,]
不看家世
or recommendations,
不查举荐
only focuses on virtue and talent.
唯以德才论
[This is a pioneering move.]
可谓是开我朝之先河
It is truly a fortune for scholars.
实乃读书人之幸事
Indeed!
是啊
I'm requested by the PM
本官奉张相之命
[to prepare a modest feast for hospitality.]
略备薄酒以作招待
[All you scholars,]
诸位弘文馆的学子们
be sure to mingle with
可要与诸位才子
each other.
多多交流啊
[Come on.]
来
[Please.]
请请请 请请请
[Here. Cheers!]
来来来 敬各位
What is the meaning of this?
这是为何意
Prince Xian
贤王殿下
has always valued scholars.
可是一向爱重读书人
He is concerned that you all
唯恐各位学子
may not find life
在襄安生活起居
in Xiang'an convenient.
不甚便利
[He specially sent this modest gift.]
特意派人送此薄礼
[You know,]
诸君
He has a
可知贤王殿下
benevolent heart.
仁心仁德啊
[So,]
各位学子
[please be sure to accept it.]
还请务必收下
Is this the gesture from you gentry?
这便是你们士族的诚意
Mr. Pan!
潘兄
Reject the PM?
张相的面子都敢拂
Ungrateful brats!
不知好歹
Wealthy families always squander.
朱门酒肉臭
They're trying to corrupt our hearts
用如此低劣的手段
with such lowly means?
就想收买腐蚀人心
You beggar!
穷小子
You should have accepted it graciously.
别敬酒不吃吃罚酒
You're the PM's lapdogs.
你们是张相的人
Are you going to resort to violence?
收买不成就行凶
Violence? Take this!
行凶 我行凶
Eat this!
行凶是吧
This is Xiang'an City,
襄安城中
the emperor's turf.
天子脚下
[Go with the flow,]
膝盖软点
[so you wouldn't suffer!]
这样你才能少受点苦
Just be smart, you bastards!
识相点吧
Who are you people?
你们又是什么人
The PM might be merciful,
张相妇人之仁
but Prince Xian is wise.
可贤王殿下英明
Threats and temptations won't work
你们几个穷酸书生
on you stupid scholars.
威逼利诱没有用
It'd be better to eliminate all of you!
杀了干净
Just for refusing to pledge allegiance to
我们只是不愿拜入
the PM and Prince Xian,
张相和贤王的门下
must we be silenced?
难道就要被灭口吗
Wipe them all!
杀
Prince Xian will not spare you!
贤王殿下不会放过你的
Hup!
驾
It's you!
是你
Greetings, mighty commander.
沈大阁领
Watch out!
小心
This assassin strikes hard and
此人暗劲蛮横
his weapons are powerful and ruthless.
暗器力道强劲狠辣
Be careful!
小心些
Yes, sir!
是
Go after him!
追
Hurry.
快
Your Highness!
殿下
I've got a note
不知是何人
pinned to the pillar.
将这字条钉在了廊柱上